Guide to the Hanna Elsa Krueger Papers 1949-1975
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Hanna Elsa Krueger Papers
1949-1975
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 429
Krueger, Hanna Elsa
4 containers. 4 linear feet of shelf space. 2930 items.
Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, drafts, reports, and other materials relating to her professional activities and administrative duties as Chief, Technical Services, 1950-1953, and Chief, Humanities, 1953-1970. Included are some papers of her successor, Ann Wierum.
Hanna Elsa Krueger was born in Hutchinson, Minnesota on April 20, 1905. She graduated from the University of Chicago with a degree in English Education in 1928. She received a Bachelor's degree in Philosophy the next year and a Bachelor of Science degree in Library Science from the University of Illinois in 1938. Her work experience included: secretary for publishing companies, assistant in the University of Illinois Library School, Assistant Librarian and Instructor in Library Science at Carroll College Library from 1938 to 1940 and Acting Librarian from 1940 to 1943. In that year she received a Master's degree from the Graduate Library School of the University of Chicago for several successive summers' work. The next two years she was Assistant Librarian and Instructor in Library Science at Western Illinois State Teachers' College. From 1945 to 1948 she was Head of the Cataloging Department at Wayne County Library, Detroit, Michigan. The following year, Miss Krueger served as Head of the Catalog and Order department.
In 1949 Miss Krueger came to Washington State University as Head of the Cataloging Department. The following year she was promoted to Chief of the Technical Services Division. From 1953 to 1970 she was Chief of the Humanities Library. She retired from Washington State University on June 30, 1970.
Her areas of professional interest were administration, reference, catalog, and teaching library science. Professional organizations in which she belonged included the American Library Association, the Pacific Northwest Library Association, and the Washington Library Association. She also was a member of the American Association of University Professors, the American Association of University Women, and the League of Women Voters.
The papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, drafts, conference materials, copies of printed material, forms, booklets, and newsletters. The papers date from 1933 to 1975 with the bulk of the material dating from 1950 to 1970. Ann Wierum, Chief of the Humanities Library after Miss Krueger retired, added to the original collection.
Major subjects in the collection are Circulation, Faculty Library Advisory Committee, Humanities Library, Inter-Library Loan, Washington State University Library Administrative Notices, Library Administrative Council, Job Descriptions, and Technical Service Division. The papers concern the development of library practices and were originally arranged as a reference file.
The Hanna Elsa Krueger Papers consist of a single series arranged alphabetically by subject.
This collection is open for research use.
The papers of Hanna Elsa Krueger were deposited with the Washington State University Libraries in 1978 (UA 78-44).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Krueger, Hanna Elsa, 1905- --Archives; Wierum, Ann
Washington State University. Library
Librarians--Washington (State)--Pullman--Correspondence
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State)
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Abel Approval Program, 1964-1969; 56 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Abstracts, 1963; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Accession Numbers, 1955; 1963; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Acquisition
  - General, 1949-1969; 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Policies, 1947-1961; 21 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Procedures, 1947-1970; 16 items. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reprint Expediting Service, 1957; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Administration, Principles, 1952-1954; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- American Association of University Professors, 1953-1968; 26 items. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- American Studies Program, 1961; 1966; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Anthropology, 1964; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Archival Administration, Symposium, 1969-1970; 7 items. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Archives, 1955-1967; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Audio-Visual
  - Aids in Education Course, 1953; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Catalog Cards, 1953-1955; 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Automation, 1967; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bibliography
  - General, 1969; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - National, 1963-1964; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Binding, 1951-1972; 15 items. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Black Studies, 1972; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Book Loss, 1960; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Book Numbers (see also Library of Congress--Classification), 1954; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Book Selection
  - Principles, 1950; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Procedures, 1954; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Weeding, 1957; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Budget, 1949-1970; 22 items. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Call-Number Distribution, 1950-1956; 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Catalog Duplication, 1952-1972; 10 items. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Cataloging
  - General, 1933-1965; 15 items. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Procedures, 1949-1954; 42 items. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Recataloging, 1951-1970; 8 items. (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Center for Research Libraries, 1967-1972; 6 items. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Central Information Desk, 1952; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Chaney, Sue--Sabbatical, 1965; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Chicano Studies, 1970; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Circulation, 1948-1974; 124 items. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Citizens' Conference on Libraries, 1969; 22 items. (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Classification, 1954-1955; 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Classification Authority File, 1964; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Coins, undated; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- College Art Association, 1954; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- College Catalogs, 1951; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- College Library
  - General, 1952-1958; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Program, 1952-1965; 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - References, 1952; 34 items. (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Compact Storage, 1957-1972; 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Computing Center News, 1968; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Conference Planning, 1953-1957; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Copyright, 1962-1968; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Current Acquistions List, 1953-1963; 11 items. (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Dedications, 1968; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Departmental Working Libraries, 1949-1954; 23 items. (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Dictionaries, 1962; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Documentation, 1953; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Dormitory Libraries, 1962; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Education
  - General, 1955; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Higher, 1956-1973; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Ethics, Professional, 1952-1958; 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Exchange, 1947-1955; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Exhibits, 1954; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Extension, 1951-1963; 20 items. (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Faculty Committees, 1957-1972; 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Faculty Committees on Improvement of Instruction, 1957-1958; 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Faculty Library Advisory Committee, 1945-1967; 176 items. (Box 1, Folder 64-66)
- Filing, 1953-1954; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Foundation for Integrated Education, 1951-1953; 12 items. (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Friends of the Library
  - General, 1962-1966; 8 items. (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Washington State University, 1939-1962; 20 items. (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Governor's Conference on Libraries, 1967-1969; 54 items. (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Holland Library, 1950; 12 items. (Box 1, Folder 72)
- Honors, 1960-1970; 9 items. (Box 2, Folder 73)
- Humanities
  - Division, undated; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Division Newsletter, v. 1-14, 1950-1964; 74 items. (Box 2, Folder 75-77)
  - General, 1954-1955; 15 items. (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Library
    - Budget Requests, 1954-1956; 10 items. (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Equipment, 1958-1969; 27 items. (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - General, 1957-1975; 21 items. (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Inventory, 1955; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Microfilms, 1966-1967; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Plans for a Humanities Divisional Reading Room, 1947; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Reports, 1952-1965; 11 items. (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Staff, 1959-1975; 55 items. (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Staff, Labor Slip, 1954-1967; 18 items. (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Statistics, 1955-1968; 43 items. (Box 2, Folder 88)
- Indexing, 1945-1969; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 89)
- Information Science, 1964-1972; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 90)
- Institute of Library Research, 1966; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 91)
- Institute of World Affairs, 1959-1966; 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 92)
- Instruction--Students, 1952-1961; 14 items. (Box 2, Folder 93)
- Instructions, 1950-1956; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 94)
- Integrated Courses
  - Biological Sciences, 1955; 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - General, 1955-1957; 8 items. (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Humanities, 1953-1961; 8 items. (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Social Science, 1950-1951; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 98)
- Intellectual Freedom, undated; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 99)
- Inter-Library Loan
  - General, 1949-1972; 145 items. (Box 2, Folder 100-102)
  - Manual, 1952-1967; 6 items. (Box 2, Folder 103)
- International Affairs Committee, 1965; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 104)
- International Education Committee, 1957-1966; 15 items. (Box 2, Folder 105)
- International Federation for Documentation, 1960-1969; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 106)
- International Federation of Library Associations, 1959-1967; 41 items. (Box 2, Folder 107)
- KWSU, 1957; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 108)
- Land Grant Colleges and Universities, 1940-1962; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 109)
- Language Laboratory, 1958; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 110)
- Latin American Cooperative Acquisitions Project, 1961-1972; 36 items. (Box 2, Folder 111)
- Lettering, undated; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 112)
- Librarian Trainee Program (WLA), 1964; 6 items. (Box 2, Folder 113)
- Librarianship, 1956-1968; 8 items. (Box 3, Folder 114)
- Libraries
  - Administration, 1939-1946; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Public, 1956; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - State and Regional, 1934-1957; 9 items. (Box 3, Folder 117)
- Library Cooperation, 1956-1972; 23 items. (Box 3, Folder 118)
- Library of Congress
  - Classification, 1951-1964; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - General, 1947-1968; 33 items. (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - MARC, undated; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 121)
- Library Surveys, 1954-1955; 6 items. (Box 3, Folder 122)
- Library Technicians, 1967; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 123)
- Library, 21, undated; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 124)
- Library, Washington State University
  - Administration
    - Library Literature Collection, 1963; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 125)
    - Notices, 1953-1969; 164 items. (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Administrative Council, 1950-1973; 350 items. (Box 3, Folder 127-130)
  - Advisory Board, 1954-1956; 18 items. (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Advisory Council
    - Committees, 1951-1969; 29 items. (Box 3, Folder 132)
    - Definition, 1953; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Building and Reorganization Plans, 1954-1973; 40 items. (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Campus Delivery System, 1971-1972; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 135)
  - Committees, 1954; 1970; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 136)
  - Handbooks, 1952-1962; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - History, 1947-1957; 15 items. (Box 3, Folder 138)
  - Library News, 1965-1971; 18 items. (Box 3, Folder 139)
  - Library Staff Association
    - General, 1950-1967; 15 items. (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - News Notes, 1949-1951; 14 items. (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Long-Range Automation Projects, 1970-1972; 13 items. (Box 3, Folder 142)
  - Manuscripts, Archives, 1949-1958; 12 items. (Box 3, Folder 143)
  - Resources Guides, 1956; 1966; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 144)
- Linguistics, 1973-1975; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 145)
- Literary Studies, undated; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 146)
- Mail, 1951; 1970; 17 items. (Box 3, Folder 147)
- Manuscripts, 1963-1967; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 148)
- Maps, 1966-1969; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 149)
- Microforms, 1951-1963; 18 items. (Box 4, Folder 150)
- Moral Rearmament Movement, 1954; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 151)
- National Advisory Committee on Libraries, 1968; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 152)
- National Library Week, 1962-1970; 6 items. (Box 4, Folder 153)
- Newspapers, 1956-1970; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 154)
- Northwest Association for Secondary and Higher Schools Accreditation Survey, 1956-1960; 16 items. (Box 4, Folder 155)
- Orton Collection, 1946-1956; 8 items. (Box 4, Folder 156)
- Orton Room--Reservations, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 157)
- Pacific Northwest Bibliographic Center, 1962-1963; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 158)
- Pacific Northwest Library Association
  - General, 1958-1970; 11 items. (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Library Development Project, 1956-1957; 6 items. (Box 4, Folder 160)
- Personnel Administration
  - Annual Review, 1957-1969; 26 items. (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Compensation, 1951-1955; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Employee Evaluation, 1954-1964; 6 items. (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Job Descriptions, 1949-1966; 140 items. (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Non-Faculty, 1949-1961; 11 items. (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Personnel Practices in State Libraries and State Library Extension Agencies, 1960; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 166)
- Personnel Policies
  - Library--Faculty, 1946-1969; 34 items. (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Library--Washington State Universtiy, 1949-1970; 33 items. (Box 4, Folder 168)
- Photoduplication, 1954-1969; 9 items. (Box 4, Folder 169)
- Public Relations, 1952; 5 items. (Box 4, Folder 170)
- Pulisher Files--Humanities Library, 1963; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 171)
- Purchase Requests, 1958-1965; 9 items. (Box 4, Folder 172)
- Quarter System, 1965; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 173)
- Reference, 1959; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 174)
- Rental Collection, 1947-1951; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 175)
- Reports
  - Hannah Krueger, 1949-1957; 5 items. (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - Library, 1947-1966; 8 items. (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - Techniques, 1947-1952; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 178)
- Research Studies of Washington State University, 1951-1953; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 179)
- Reserve Books, 1959-1968; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 180)
- Scheduling, 1958-1964; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 181)
- Science Library, 1952-1961; 5 items. (Box 4, Folder 182)
- Searching--Procedures, 1955; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 183)
- Seminar on the Acquisition of Latin American Library Materials, 1960-1966; 6 items. (Box 4, Folder 184)
- Serials
  - General, 1956-1970; 5 items. (Box 4, Folder 185)
  - Procedures, 1949-1964; 9 items. (Box 4, Folder 186)
- Shelving, 1966-1968; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 187)
- Short Title Catalog, 1963; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 188)
- Smoking Policy in Library, 1964; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 189)
- Society for Theatre Research, 1956-1965; 14 items. (Box 4, Folder 190)
- Special Libraries Association, 1950-1962; 8 items. (Box 4, Folder 191)
- Statistics--Library, 1954-1969; 17 items. (Box 4, Folder 192)
- Superscriptions, 1953-1954; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 193)
- Technical Service Division, 1946-1969; 91 items. (Box 4, Folder 194)
- Textbooks, undated; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 195)
- Theses, Washington State University, 1964; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 196)
- Translating, 1963-1964; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 197)
- Union Catalog, 1936-1947; 25 items. (Box 4, Folder 198)
- United States Book Exchange, 1950-1965; 5 items. (Box 4, Folder 199)
- Vocational Library, 1947; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 200)
- Washington Library Association, 1970; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 201)
- Washington (State). Washington State Advisory Council on Libraries, 1972; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 202)
- Washington State University
  - Administrative Notices, 1952-1970; 11 items. (Box 4, Folder 203)
  - Computing Center, undated; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 204)
  - General, 1954-1975; 23 items. (Box 4, Folder 205)
  - Planning Council, 1968; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 206)
- Washington State University Press, 1972; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 207)
- Washington State University Women's Club, 1970; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 208)
- Whitman County Library, 1963; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 209)